So, this, uh,
sutta I'm bringing up
I'm bringing up
cuz I'm interested in the topic of
cessation of contact. Mhm.
And it's, uh, Anguttara 663 called the
Penetrative Penetrative Penetrative
Discourse. And
So, it says,
"Sensual pleasure pleasures should be
understood. This
This
feelings should be understood.
Perceptions should be understood. The
taints should be understood. Karma
should be understood. Suffering should
be understood."
So, these are these six
topics that need to be understood. But,
also the source and origin of sensual
the source and origin of sensual
pleasures and so on
should be understood. The diversity of
sensual pleasures and so on should be
understood. The result
The result
should be understood. The cessation
should be understood. And the way
leading to the cessation should be
understood. All those six things.
All those six things.
Yeah, you got to all those things there.
So, first and foremost
should be understood.
Yeah. So.
So, person should ask himself, "What is
understanding? What is the nature of
understanding?" But, those those, yeah.
But, those those, yeah.
But, through that kind of questioning of
what is the source and origin of sensual
pleasures? What is the diversity in
sensual pleasures? What is the result?
What is the cessation? What is the way
leading to the cessation? So, you can be
thinking about these things. Yeah.
Questioning this. Yeah, but I'm I'm I'm
just trying to highlight that
it should be understood, must be
understood. Not like, "Oh, I had this
experience of freedom from centrality and I haven't
of freedom from centrality and I haven't
understood it." Yeah, so why does it
need to be understood? Cuz that's the
only way to free yourself from it. The
lack of understanding is the root of
everything that that you want to be free from. But
that that you want to be free from. But
the lack of understanding is the root of
the So that's what I mean, like you know,
So that's what I mean, like you know,
when people practice the Dharma, they
practice with this notion of you're
going to have a special experience as a
result of whatever methods and effort
you're making, then you're going to have
these revelations and
you will not have any revelations that
matter uh unless you make the effort to
uh unless you make the effort to
understand and then your revelations
will be, "Ah, now I understood it. Ah,
okay." That's what's interesting. That's
why Um
uh what's the what's the other one? The
feeling. That's what feeling is. Ah,
okay. That's the nature of the feeling.
But that's the nature of of things to be
perceived. You need to understand it.
Not like just do random stuff and then
these these results will magically occur
to you.
So how do you That's what I mean, like
you asked yourself, "What is
understanding? Like how do I understand
anything?" Can I follow a set of
Can I follow a set of
sort of prescribed motions
and arrive at understanding if I do step
one, step two, step three? No.
And everybody knows that. You just
recall back in the when you were in the
school when they when they sort of
kind of parrot you things out that you
must memorize. And you memorize it and
you repeat or you get a top mark and you
haven't understood a clue.
You You haven't actually made that
internal connection to it that you
recognize the nature of it.
And then give it some time and you don't
remember a single thing. Even while
you're still in school, by the way. But
things you understood
you still remember 30, 40 years later.
But why do you remember it? Because they
were understood. But why were they
understood? Exactly. So why would it
What is the difference then? What is the
difference between knowing something,
having information about it
and uh actually understanding it?
How you How you
Yeah, the difference is that you Well,
the difference is you know it. Yeah.
Basically, understanding means knowing
that thing in the nature, not just in
the content.
So, understanding the nature of whatever
content you collected through
information. So, that's like the most general
So, that's like the most general
description of what understanding is.
So, if you never look for the nature,
but you only focus on the content
of your methods, of your techniques, of
your emotions, of your observances,
and then you hope for a new content to
be that understanding of the practice
and and liberation of Nibbana,
and it's not.
The Buddha did not use a different word.
It's the word for understanding. Same
word used when when a craftsman
understands his craft. He knows the
principle behind the chariot making. He
understands it. He doesn't need to think
about it. He just makes it cuz he
understood that it works like that. In
its nature, that's the result. But how
does he understand it? By making effort
to understand.
If you never make Wait, what is the
nature of this? Yeah, I know.
I have all the content, all the
information, but what is the nature of
that? What are the characteristics of that
What are the characteristics of that
nature?
What is it for? What is this thing?
Yeah. What is the purpose? What is my
What is basically behind this content?
Oh, like sensuality needs to be
understood. So, question.
Sense desire needs to be understood.
Okay, sense desire. So, you can relate
to sense desire.
I had sense desires in the past. I have
sense desires now. What are the sense
desires? I see sense desire in the
future. Ask yourself, am I liable to sense
Ask yourself, am I liable to sense
desire in the future? Ask yourself, so
what is a sense desire?
Oh, sense desire is when I go after
agreeable objects of my senses.
Agreeable sight, sound, smell, taste,
touches. Okay, so
what is
determined? What is determined that agreeability?
What is determined that agreeability?
What is that agreeability determined by?
The agreeability.
Oh, this is agreeable, this is
disagreeable. That's just how things present
That's just how things present
themselves, pretty much. So, where is
your sense desire then? Is it in the
agreeable or disagreeable?
Or is it in you wanting the agreeable
and not wanting the disagreeable?
Because if desire is truly in that
thing in that agreeability or disagreeability,
in that agreeability or disagreeability,
it would be kind of there would be
nothing for you to do.
Just having the experience of the sight
of agreeable nature would be enclosed in
itself. That would be the agreeable
experience. You wouldn't need or you
wouldn't be able to want more of it.
Because any notion between agreeable and
more of it is already contained within
the sight.
So there is no room there for
self-awareness. Oh, I want this on
account of that.
But the fact is when you have agreeable
sight, you want more of it.
You want to touch it as well. You want
to taste it if it's edible.
You want to smell it. Mhm.
Oh, why is that? Cuz it's just the
sight. So how does sight make you want
to So it's you who wants to do all of
that on top of it. So then you realize,
okay, so sense desire is not in
beautiful things in the world.
Sense desire is in my attitude towards
As in I can't just help myself but
automatically go towards it. Same like
moth sees the light.
Doesn't think, just go straight.
Can't help himself. It's still moth's
responsibility, by the way.
It's not that the light makes you,
commands you, controls you, takes over
your actions.
No, you just can't help yourself.
So then you realize, oh, you're already
now practicing and understanding.
So if I if I understand that sensual
pleasures, that sensual desire
If you understand what sensual desire is
You you know the escape. Well, then you
will the escape will become apparent.
So what is the escape? From sensuality?
Well, it's exactly it's not
it's removal of the assumption that
sense pleasures are in things.
That's like the first the basis for any
any escape.
The only reason you don't escape it The
only reason you're still entangled is
cuz you don't see where the trap is, so
you step in it.
Once you learn what's really the trap
and what it isn't, then you'll know how
to not step in it.
So the trap is your own desire that you
assume to be in those things. And by not
seeing where it actually is, you're
fully already trapped.
By not seeing that it's your attitude
that's the root of your desire.
What about the pressure? Remember you
You spoke about
Well, pressure, see, pressure is kind of
secondary, so to speak.
So in the experience of, say, agreeable
sight, Mhm.
you are pressured
because you have been going after the
agreeability of your senses by default.
So contact, passa, or pressure,
whichever you want to translate it,
um
has been maintained
through you ignoring where the desire
is. Now the the
Now the the
it's even worse because there is no
first point in our experience as a
whole, in the entire samsara, before
which you did not ignore things and then
you started ignoring. There is no first
point before which you were not
pressured and then you became pressured.
So although pressure is secondary, it
was always first. Ignorance is
secondary, yet it was always first. By
not knowing that, that's why it was
first. So that's why there is no discernable
So that's why there is no discernable
point, manifestation, first moment when
ignorance manifests, when avidya
manifests, as the Buddha described it.
But once you realize that, oh,
the only reason I'm pressured is cuz
I've been giving in to the pressure.
Mhm. If I stop giving in to the pressure for
If I stop giving in to the pressure for
agreeable, pressure for getting rid of
the disagreeable, that pressure will
fade cuz I'm not fueling it anymore. If
the pressure fades,
any assumption that you jumped into by
giving into the pressure will have to
disappear as well. And then you get to
see, ah, sense desires were always
unpleasant.
They will always be unpleasant. There
was never anything different. It was me
misperceiving them.
Like the
man affected with leprosy
burning embers are providing him
pleasure, although they're not. So, he
realizes these burning embers were
always uncomfortable and painful,
always. It's just because of my wrong view,
It's just because of my wrong view,
misperception, I was regarding that
genuine sharp pain as pleasant.
So, all of this already, ah, that's how
you understand things.
Questioning, looking for the nature,
discerning the characteristics,
questioning further.
Yeah. Day and night, first watch of the
night, second watch of the night, just
purifying, as the Buddha said, his mind
from the unwholesome state. What is the
fundamental unwholesome state? Lack of
understanding is.
Ignorance is.
That is the root of all unwholesome.
Mhm. So, you purify your mind by removing
So, you purify your mind by removing
your own self-induced ignoring of the
nature of things.
What is the nature of aversion?
What is the nature of anger?
What is the nature of choice?
What is the nature of
feeling? What is the nature of perceiving?
What is the nature of perceiving?
What is the nature of it? Not just what
is perceiving, what is feeling. What is
the nature of it?
What is a universal characteristic of
feeling that is present there as its
nature regardless of what's being what
is being specifically felt?
What is the universal nature of
perception? Regardless of what sense is
perceiving and what is being perceived
through that sense.
So, so for example just on the
Um
What is Okay, uh sorry.
What is the cessation of sensual
pleasures? Mhm.
Mhm.
What is the cessation of the Cessation
of desire and delight. Cessation of with
cessation of contact. Cessation of
pressure. Cessation of with cessation of
pressure contact.
Is the cessation of sensual pleasures?
That's what I said. Yeah. If you if you
stop habitually going after the
agreeable, you are inadvertently
you are inadvertently
not fueling the pressure anymore. You
By not fueling the pressure,
you won't be pressured to act anymore.
That's the diminishing of pressure.
Exactly. Diminishing
So through through developing
understanding and seeing clearly, the
pressure will fade away.
Cessation, fading away of pressure, is
then cessation fading away of the
necessary basis for sense desires. Mhm.
Can you have a desire without implicit
pressure? Say it again.
Impossible. So where does the pressure come from?
So where does the pressure come from?
I'm just asking in a different way.
Where does the Well,
yeah. You want to ask really It doesn't
come from as in it comes and now it's
here. It's there because that which
determines it it's there. Mhm. The
sankhara or the pressure is there. So,
what is determining or where how does
How is pressure maintained?
What is its What is the necessary basis
for pressure? It's uh perception of
agreeable and disagreeable.
The necessary basis Yeah. is the
perception So, what is the necessary base of
So, what is the necessary base of
perception of agreeable and
disagreeable? Senses.
Eyes, nose, ears, body, mouth. And
what's the necessary base for senses?
Well, you can go further now, but it's
going to become too abstract for people.
Let's stick with the what you can relate
to. Senses.
Senses.
So, can you have perception of agreeable
or disagreeable if you don't have the
eyes?
Inconceivable. So, the necessary basis
for your loves and your hates
is being able to see.
Yet, that's not how you regard your
loves and your hates.
They're far more important. They're put
first. Although they're always within
Although they're always within
the domain of sight and eyes,
it's actually more important to you.
You see that as more fundamental. What I
love and what I hate.
So, you've been ignoring the right the
nature of that the the the relationship
for so long
that now you don't even see that it's
actually the other way around. You turn
the whole picture upside down. That is
dependent. That which is a second you put first.
That which is a second you put first.
That which is dependent you put as the
the kind of fundamental determinant.
But it's actually being determined.
So, what is determining
that pressure?
Again, it's It's the fact that you have
eyes and senses. So, that's not not
enough in itself. Now, that that still
fairly abstract. It would probably be
for most people. So, now you want to
dwell on the nature of that sankhara of
eyes of the six sense base.
What is the nature now of those eyes?
Now, again, Connect with it, so to
speak. Understand it.
And then everything else that's being
determined by it cannot remain
indifferent to it. Has to be affected by
that understanding.
So, what is the nature of your senses?
What is the nature of perception?
Are you are you in control?
Yeah, but yeah, yeah. But as you're
saying, that's that's you should go deep
you go deep in the questioning. You go
deep that. So, anyway, it started off
with sensuality, questioning sensuality.
That it's
But then it goes to
questioning feelings and then
questioning perceptions. So, the nature
of your
nature of your feelings, then it's
questioning the nature of your
perceptions.
But it you it's just questioning
sensuality. It would take you every
Yeah, of course. See the whole thing.
So,
So, anyway, it's going to go on to
feelings. Uh so, feelings should be understood. Um
Um
You know, what is the source and origin
of feelings?
Pressure is the source and origin of feelings.
is the source and origin of feelings.
Yeah.
Pressure.
That is why
it is felt
something is felt because
of that pressure.
Yeah, pressure is already felt.
Pressure is what's felt.
Feeling is the pressure. Right.
So, the cessation of pressure is a
cessation of sensual pleasures. But
also, It's a cessation of of that
misperception. It's a cessation of feeling.
It's a cessation of feeling.
Yeah.
So, not only that that pressure
ceases or diminishes,
that uh
feeling diminishes.
Because that's the thing. Agreeable
perception. Agreeable, disagreeable
that is felt in regard to perception,
in regard to what's perceived,
that's in itself. There's nothing
Disagreements does not bother you in
itself. Mhm. Agreeable does not pull you towards
Mhm. Agreeable does not pull you towards
it in itself, either.
But it's you being pressured by it means
you're feeling it. Means you are pulled.
You are being repelled and so on.
So, removal, cessation of that pressure
through clear understanding
will make you then not feel
disagreeable as pain. Mhm. It will then
make you not feel the agreeable as
sensual delight for more of it.
It will make you not feel the neutral
feeling unpleasantly.
Cessation of of pressure through
understanding.
Yeah, the only way to look for pressure
to cease is to understand the nature of
it. To not put it first, but see there's
To not put it first, but see there's
determined by something else that's not
in your control.
It also be spoke recently about the
non-reactive attitude.
attitude.
Yeah, you have to have non-reactive
attitude as in not not
not jumping into pleasure,
not trying to deny the pain. That's the
only way you can understand it. That's
only way how you're going to be able to
allow it to endure for what it is.
So, that you can understand it. So, it's
clear without you
It's a prerequisite. So, you and you you
not reacting out of pressure is will not
necessarily result in you understanding
pressure. But, certainly there can be no
But, certainly there can be no
understanding unless you stopped
reacting first.
But, those those two things are
non-reaction. Mhm.
And Non-reaction will make you then will
Non-reaction will make you then will
make you endure it.
Having something endure means becoming
more familiar with it whether you want
it or not. Yeah.
Right. But, that would be difficult
with it means oh, you can look closer
and closer and get to understand it
without just habitually, reactively
trying to either have more of it or less
of it or ignore it.
The the thing becomes clearer and you
can see it in its detail.
The reason why people don't understand
the nature of sensuality is because by
default you go to it.
The reason why people don't understand
the nature of ill will and anger is by
default you act out of it.
You need to stop doing that. That's not
optional. Or you or neutral feeling you close.
Or you or neutral feeling you close.
Neutral feeling, you basically you want
to get rid of it by distracting yourself
from it cuz it's just too unbearable.
Try and hide from it. Try and hide from
it, yeah.
Try and replace it. So, what's
So, what's
is the result of feelings?
Well, choices you make on account of it.
This The answer answer here is yeah.
One produces
an individual existence
That's a weird translation. that
corresponds with whatever feelings one
experiences and which may be the
consequence either of merit or demerit.
One chooses. Right, yeah. Makes one's
choices. One chooses and acts out of that choice
One chooses and acts out of that choice
is the result of the
the feelings.
Which obviously can be meritorious,
demeritorious, or neither meritorious
nor non-meritorious.
Like neutral action, neither good nor
bad. But acting out of feelings
But acting out of feelings
one performs action.
One decides action. And the Buddha said
every action is all intentional already.
One is creating karma.
choice your choice is already your
karma. Yeah.
So, you can choose to act further out of
that choice, which is another set of
choices on top of your choices, but even
your fundamental choice it's already
your karma. It's already an action.
So, that's where you remove the
pressure, you remove the necessary basis
for acting out of pressure. How can you
act out of pressure if there is no
pressure felt? There we There's the
ending of karma. Ending of karma there
and then. You don't need to wait for the
samsara to sort of
run out or something like that. You
ended it by stepping outside of it, by
not feeling it anymore, by not partaking
in it anymore, by not deciding upon it
anymore, by not perceiving it anymore,
by not perceiving it anymore,
misperceiving it and by not reacting and
understanding. reacting, yeah. By not reacting, you get
reacting, yeah. By not reacting, you get
to understand it. Once you understood
it, well, then reacting becomes
impossible.
It continues about perceptions.
Perceptions should be understood.
And what is the source and origin of
perceptions? Mhm.
Mhm.
So, you said before contact, pressure
Mhm. is the source of perception.
Mhm. Well, of the perception. As I said,
there is no first point
when these perceptions became bad
Mhm. and misperceived. Your perception
is misperception. Right. Your feeling is
misfeeling, so to speak. Your intention
is misintention. Yeah, it's misfelt.
But it's only like you can only call it
it's only like you can only call it
misperception, misfeeling, and and
misintention from the arahant's point of
view. But you have to be one or the other
But you have to be one or the other
either. We're not talking about theory,
in which case, yes, it's true to say
that these perceptions don't exist in an
arahant and so on.
But you don't start from a neutral position.
you don't start from a neutral position.
You don't start by Somebody who's
affected with ignorance cannot start
from a position they can understand
arahant, puthujjana, and then choose to
walk to arahant. You know, you start
fully enclosed in the state of
puthujjana. So, any perception that you
can have is the misperception resulting
out of pressure. Any feeling that you
have is a is basically misfeeling
resulting out of pressure. Any choice
that you have, any intention that you
have, it's a misintention resulting out
of pressure.
Which is why then the Buddha would say,
when he was teaching somebody who is not
an arahant yet, he would call the
cessation of the five aggregates. He
would say, "Feeling ceases, perception
ceases, intention cease."
Right. Yeah. Because they do. Yeah.
From that point of view, those type of
feeling, intention, perception rooted in
pressure, they're gone. So, it's true to
say that those uh
uh type of those feeling perception
intention they don't exist anymore.
They're not.
But that's not to say that Arahat is
sort of like a There's no perception.
robot robot who doesn't perceive
anything. No, it's just that perception
that he has, the only way to relate to
it is to become an Arahat yourself. You
cannot understand it even theoretically
because theoretical understanding is
still affected by your misperception
rooted in depression. Right.
So, yeah. The beginning of perception
needs to be understood thus because I
don't understand thus I don't
the perception, you will uproot the
pressure and the perception that was
being determined by that pressure. Mhm.
Cuz that's what I mean, like
speaking in that kind of um
like say a a theoretical model
perception comes first, feeling comes
first, intention comes first. They're
the aggregates there.
There is no
pressure in in the five aggregates.
Cannot be.
They're like five heaps, exist on their
own. Arise and fall as Buddha said.
But that's not your starting position.
Your starting position is that all of
those aggregates, they're not
independent of you and of each other
are taken up
by the pressure, by the assumptions.
Yeah, come. And see, by
taking them up means you put second as
first. So, the pressure, which is really
dependent only because there are things
that can pressure you
like perception, feeling, intentions.
Like, can you be pressured if there's no
perception? Can you be pressured if
there's nothing felt? Can you be
pressured if there are no intentions?
Impossible. Mhm. If there are no ways of manifesting
Mhm. If there are no ways of manifesting
pressure, there can be no pressure
manifested. As simple as that.
As simple as that.
But you put that pressure first. So, all
of that pressure is determined by the
ability basically to be pressured, so to
speak. You assume that pressure is
first, so you keep acting out of
pressure. And whenever you act out of
pressure, you assume pressure first and
then everything else that you act on
account of is second.
So, and if anything you perceive,
anything you feel, anything you intend
is actually made subordinate by your own
view to the pressure. Why? Because the
ultimate goal is getting rid of the
discomfort of the pressure.
But discomfort of the pressure, which is
what? Have you created it? No. Are you
subjected to So, you are a victim on its
own. Yeah. How? Oh, well, through what I
perceived, through what I felt, through
what I intended.
That's basically a vicious circle.
Mhm. You create the pressure by not
You create the pressure by not
understanding perception, feeling,
intention. You are pressured.
But by being pressured and acting out of
pressure, you then maintain perception,
feeling, intention that fuel that
provide the basis for pressure, that
makes them more, that makes the basis
bigger, and and that's how pressure
proliferates and grows. That's like the
updana. The more fuel for the fire there is, the
The more fuel for the fire there is, the
bigger the fire.
The more fuel is consumed, the more fuel
is found, the bigger the fire grows.
But fire is not the fuel.
Updana is not in the aggregates, as the
Buddha said, but he said there is no
updana anywhere apart from the
aggregates. Desire and lust in regard to the
Desire and lust in regard to the
aggregates, as in acting out of the
value that your desire must be satisfied,
that your desire must be satisfied,
desire to achieve, desire to get rid of
makes everything else subordinate to
that desire. All the desire is second to
everything else.
You made it first and now everything
else is second. So, all of these
aggregates as second, perception as
second, feeling as second
intentions as second will cease once you
remove the pressure.
Because if you have them as second and
you don't make them you don't understand
them, they will keep fueling the
pressure, they will keep taking itself
as first.
So, that's why I said like you are
pressured because you perceive and you
feel and you intend.
But the perception, feeling, and
intention are that pressure. That's how
pressure manifests.
I got that image of it's you you have a
twisted view of things. Mhm. Upside down
the whole everything's the wrong way
around. Yeah. Or twisted out of shape.
Yeah. And that's the pressure. Is that
And that's the pressure. Is that
Yeah. So all those twisted shapes will
cease. Yeah.
Yeah.
And when things turn right way around
the right way.
you remove the that force that's been
twisting them.
Yeah. So it's not bent out of shape.
So it's not bent out of shape.
Yeah. So it's not like your aggregates
get replaced by something. Aggregates
remain aggregates. Ignorant aggregates,
arahant's aggregates,
aggregates are there.
Feelings there, perceptions there,
intentions there.
But now they're seen for what they are.
They're not put second. They're seen as
They're seen. Yeah. The
Again, what is the cessation
of perceptions? Cessation of
What is the cessation of misperception?
Yeah. Well, no, I don't want to call it
perception, feeling, and intention
because by saying misperception allows
person who hasn't understood perception,
feeling, and intention
Mhm. to think they can pertain to
to think they can pertain to
understanding of correct
perception, feeling, and intention of an
arahant. Before before, yeah. No, the
only perception you know is the
perception are you free from pressure or
not? If the answer is no, means your
If the answer is no, means your
perception, your feeling, your intention
are second to it.
So cessation of feeling, intention, and
perception for an ignorant mind
is achieved through cessation of the
pressure of ignorant mind.
Mhm. So how do you free yourself from
pressure? By understanding.
By understanding.
Yes. How do you arrive at an
understanding?
Trying to understand.
Okay, but
what is a necessary base for you to try
to understand correctly?
That restraint. Yeah, by not acting out
of pressure. I don't react to that, as I
see. Exactly.
Exactly.
So, I just reiterate in the same cuz
it's not an easy topic.
No, no, no.
So, you don't act out of pressure.
See, even you haven't understood the
pressure, but inadvertently taking it on
faith that you shouldn't act out of
pressure, you're you're ceasing to
provide the basis for proliferation of
that pressure.
You're ceasing to provide the basis for
that misperception, misfeeling, and
misintention. I think, "Oh, there is the real
I think, "Oh, there is the real
intention, real perception." Yeah,
theoretically there is, practically
there isn't. That's not my concern right
now. Your concern is not cultivate the
pressure, action out of pressure
anymore, understand the pressure, and
then that feeling, perception, intention
that are left after you
you're free from pressure,
then you wouldn't call it perception,
feeling, intention if those are the
designations used for the ones that were
pressured in the past.
That's why
five aggregates cease.
For an arahant, the puthujjana's five
aggregates have ceased completely. But
from puthujjana's point of view, that
means, "Oh, this is like the ultimate
nothingness." That's why people would
freak out.
When they would get the sense for the
Buddhist teaching, so they would kill
us, they would make me disappear. Cuz
any relation they can have with the idea
of themself is the idea of these
misperceived things. Things that are put
second while they're actually first.
So, if you have a Hold on. If you have a
recognition that, "Oh, that would be
removed," then you think, "I will be removed," and
then you think, "I will be removed," and
that freaks you out.
But why would you be doing that?
Why do you freak out? Oh, cuz you want
to get rid of that discomfort which
pressures you.
Both down to the same principle. Yeah.
Yeah. And really that's what you want to be
And really that's what you want to be
free of. You don't want to be
Exactly. You want to be free of
something. So
So again when you ask when someone asks
or is concerned with the state of an
arahant It's irrelevant.
So who cares? It's It's irrelevant if
you're concerned on the level of
collecting information so you can
clarify what your goal should be. Yeah.
But if you're concerned on the level of
satisfying the craving for my answer
you're just acting out of pressure. So
no amount of knowledge of an arahant
will make you anything closer to him.
That's why if you start thinking hold on
I can get all the knowledge about an
arahant. The only way to understand an arahant is
The only way to understand an arahant is
to become at least a sotapanna.
Preferably become an arahant myself.
That's the only way you can understand
an arahant. So don't waste If that's
your goal then then you'll start looking
in the right direction. That's why I
keep saying you should not think you are
practicing the Dhamma. You can practice
the Dhamma unless you release the
sotapanna. You should think that I can practice the
You should think that I can practice the
Dhamma if I become a sotapanna. That's
That's my goal.
But if you think I'm not a sotapanna but
I can practice the Dhamma
means you allow yourself that kind of
space in between for which you have no
measure. Cuz the only measure of the Dhamma is
Cuz the only measure of the Dhamma is
knowing what Dhamma is which is
sotapatti. As the Buddha said countless amount of
As the Buddha said countless amount of
time. Yet here you are know that you
don't know what the Dhamma is but at the
same time refuse to give up the idea
that you are practicing the Dhamma that
you don't know what it is.
And because of that you will not push
yourself in the right direction whereby
there will be no compromise in between
and then no I have to become a sotapanna
in order to practice Dhamma.
Because if you think you can practice
Dhamma without being a sotapanna
you'll not make the effort to become a
sotapanna. And becoming a sotapanna is the
And becoming a sotapanna is the
necessary basis for beginning the
practice of the Dhamma.
Here it comes to number the fourth
one is the taint should be understood.
The way aka the source and origin.
What and what is the diversity of
taints? There are taints leading to hell,
There are taints leading to hell,
leading to the animal realm,
leading to the realm of ghosts, human
world, or God the God realm. Yeah.
That's something that people get
confused, you know, like
levels of desire so to speak.
Oh, so you now you say acting out of
desire is bad. Yes, that's true.
But that's not to say that all desire is
equally bad.
That's not to say that all of the taints
are equally bad.
Some are worse than the other. Some
taints take you to hell. Some taints
take you to God's realm.
They're still taints.
So that's when you like when some of
these people hear us, oh desire is bad,
I must be free from desire. Well, isn't
practice of Dharma desire?
And so what? Yes, it is and
it is everything is rooted in desire.
But there is a desire that's not as bad
as sensual desire.
Because it's not as bad as sensual
sensual desire, you can actually start
to do things that will allow the mind
the desire in itself.
And you'll be free from desire.
So yes, you wanted to be free from
desire is your own desire.
What do you do now?
But usually people say, oh, isn't
wanting to practice Dharma desire? Means
I can't do anything about it, so I go
back to sensual. No, there are different
levels. So why don't you then choose a
better desire on account of worse
desire? That's what you should do.
Oh, so practicing the Dharma is a
desire. Wanting to have a sexual intercourse is
Wanting to have a sexual intercourse is
a desire. Yeah, but they're not the same
level desires. So, ask yourself which
desires are better than than the others
that I have. And then do the better
ones. Yeah. And then find even better desires.
You start refining, exactly.
That's that's the diversity of desire,
the diversity of the taints. And that's
what Buddha meant, desire is to be
abandoned by the means of desire.
Craving is to be abandoned by the means
of craving.
Um what was it now? Conceit is to be
abandoned by the means of conceit. You
hear that such and such became an
arahant. What?
If he can do it, I can do it.
That's a completely conceited thought,
because of which now
you start looking into arahantship. You
start suddenly so you start restraining
your senses, you start dwelling on the
nature of things, including the nature
of your own conceit that made you dwell
on the nature of conceit.
And then you end up freeing yourself
through your understanding of it. So,
yes, conceit resulted in canceling the
conceit by thinking in the right
direction. But it's not the same conceit as someone
But it's not the same conceit as someone
who is So,
so extremely arrogant.
Exactly. Who totally recognizes that I'm
free I'm free from something. I'm ready
in the path. And that's means see,
knowing that means understanding the
diversity of conceit. Understanding the
diversity of desire, understanding the
diversity of taints. Yeah, it's
different, yeah. Because ah okay, so
yes, this all partakes in the nature of
conceit, this all partakes in the nature
of craving, this all partakes in the
nature of desire, this all partakes in
the nature of taints.
But it's not to say that all the taints
because of that are the same.
That's like seeing that two different
contents share the same nature, and then you
share the same nature, and then you
choose to ignore that they're different
contents.
A content of this
action rooted in craving
takes you to hell, it's murder. It
doesn't mean the same.
You you you murder somebody out of
desire. You eat food out of desire.
You eat food out of desire.
In its nature, shares the same nature.
It's rooted in desire. In its content,
it's a very different thing. One is
murder, another one is just eating food.
So, which one is better?
Then, do the better one.
You replace a coarser Exactly. desire
with That's why the whole point of sensory
That's why the whole point of sensory
strength and precepts, you have to
replace bad action with good action.
It's still an action.
Action, yeah.
Or sometimes then you have people
develop a belief that good action,
simply replacing the bad action, is how
you free yourself from action. And
that's impossible as well.
No amount of action can free you from
action unless it's the action that makes
you understand the nature of action.
We're getting to that. We're getting to
that. Maybe we'll go into that.
There's a lot here. So,
let's just get back onto the diversity
then. So, that's like when when
sometimes people
you hear that you must be free from
desire, and then you think
and then you think
all desire must stop immediately.
And then you get paralyzed, you don't
know what to do. Same, you hear that you
need to be sensory restrained means I
must stop seeing, hearing, smelling,
tasting, touching things. That's
impossible.
Mhm. So, what do I do then? Well,
discern the diversity of the desire.
Right. Discern the diversity of your
motivation. Yeah, why are you doing this?
Yeah, why are you doing this?
Is this rooted in me meet sort of like
unwholesomely satisfying my sensuality
or some practical need? Where is it
rooted in?
So, same thing, for example, eating.
Like what Buddha said, you should
reflect upon the reasons why you eat the
food. Yeah. That's it. So, it's the same
Yeah. That's it. So, it's the same
thing, same content,
but one is a good action, another one is
bad action. Mhm. Both are desire.
You have desire to be alive as opposed
to you have desire to make have this
pleasurable taste.
Okay, so desire to be alive trumps
desire for pleasurable taste.
Why? Oh, because if I'm alive, I can get
to understand the nature of desire and
be free from it, and then I'll be
enlightened. Also, yeah, it's a better desire. It's
Also, yeah, it's a better desire. It's
more practical. There's a need for it.
Well, I need this life and health to
some extent so that I can practice and
basically undo this life and health.
Not be dependent upon it.
So, start discerning the diversity of
your intentions, your desires, your
cravings. See, another reason why people
See, another reason why people
intentionally or kind of ignorantly
try to ignore the diversity of one's
craving is because then
um
levels it all, like puts it on a plain
field. Thus, see
Thus, see
um craving in itself has to be the
whatever you do, you do through craving.
So, I might as well then, you know, not
be celibate.
Well, it's it's cravings here, cravings
there, cravings anywhere. Nature of
craving is in everything I want to do,
so I might as well be careless and
non-sensory straight.
No, there is a difference. Yes, all is
all you all with this craving, all with
this desire.
Now, discern within that
the worst content of that desire and the
better content.
Which one will lead me out?
Well, which one will make this desire
proliferate less?
Which one will make me make this desire
pressure me less?
Cuz see, when sensuality presents
itself, you have desire to follow it, or
you can choose to not follow it.
So, you can develop desire for
renunciation. And that's what the Buddha said. You
And that's what the Buddha said. You
replace the desire for sensuality with
your renunciation.
Choice. Yeah, the choice.
There's no desire without choice.
or demerit? There's no desire without
choice, there's no choice without
desire. better for me?
better for me?
Which choice is better?
Exactly. Which choice is better? Yeah.
For what I what my goal is at the time.
Yeah. The clearer you are about your
values and your goal, the clearer you'll
be about choices and responsibilities.
So, so you don't have to worry about it.
All desires or what do I do then?
See, question what do I do then is
another desire then. Desire to figure
this out.
So, what you do then is don't stop
making things worse
through your careless choices and
careless desires.
Create careless acts out of your
desires. Uh
Uh
what is the cessation of taints?
The cessation of ignorance. Mhm.
The cessation of taints. Yeah.
It's understanding those things.
The only way.
Not having a not not having a special
experience, you know, or I had
experience of cessation. Yeah, but what
does that mean? Have you understood it?
Yeah. What I do is special.
have experience of cessation?
If it's not understood, means it's not
cessation. Mhm.
Mhm.
Cuz they already said cessation is
understanding of those things.
So, have you understood it? If so,
convey it to me, please. Understanding
is the diminishing of ignorance. Yeah,
which is what cessation is.
But more often than not, people are
like, "Oh, cessation is this experience
when everything has ceased."
And now I need to understand that and
find my way of interpreting it. Means
you haven't understood it.
Means your experience of cessation has
arisen for you.
Has nothing has ceased.
You just added more.
Well, that's quite funny.
It's a it's a contradiction in terms.
My a special
weird experience that I had during my
intense meditation.
Exactly. If you say I had the ending of
ignorance. Yeah. I had like when people
Yeah, I had experience when everything
is ceased. I had experience of
nothingness. So, how can you talk about it?
So, how can you talk about it?
What are you designating if there is
nothing there?
If there was nothing there, what what
are you aware of?
There has to be something for you to be
aware of it. Mhm. Which means when you
say cessation, when you say it's
nothing, it's actually very much
something. Yeah.
But No, no, no. Nothing has ceased. I
will Nothing that you kind of
commonly know
was there.
But means an uncommon a novelty
experience was replaced.
Ignorance has ceased in regard to that
thing. So, when the Buddha said
So, when the Buddha said
when he talks about nothingness and
cessation, it's always cessation of
these things that determine your
experience of something or anything.
So, it's cessation of ignorance,
cessation of lust, cessation of
aversion, cessation of delusion, not the
experience of cessation.
Which you're very much lust for or
averse if somebody attacks it, or ignore
it if he starts making you doubt it.
Mhm. Mhm.
It's not the experience of cessation,
it's cessation of greed, aversion,
delusion in regard to any experience as
such. Doesn't matter.
And so, number five only.
What is
karma, action should be understood?
Choice should be understood. Choice
should be understood.
It is volition because that I call
action. Intention is
Chetana, yeah? Yeah. Action. Intention
is action. For having
intended one acts by body, speech, or
mind. Chetana, strictly speaking, is intention
Chetana, strictly speaking, is intention
or intention. Intention or intention.
So, choice. Yeah. See, when you're
making a choice, you have all these
possible ways of intending. Yeah. I can
intend it for this or for this or for
this or for this. Doesn't matter.
So, I choose to intend this given
intention. And that's your choice. You choose to
And that's your choice. You choose to
make a choice on account of present
possibilities. Each possibility is an
intention. Intentionally choosing that intention is
Intentionally choosing that intention is
what chetana is and that's already
karma. That's already where your karma
is rooted.
So, what is the origin of
action? Contact. Pressure.
Contact. Pressure.
Pressure. Pressure is the origin of your
choice. And that's what I mean. You
choose out of the value of I must be free from
out of the value of I must be free from
the discomfort of the pressure. That's a
gratuitous value
that's maintained through ignoring it.
That's why whatever you choice do you
make, you make it on account of how you
feel and trying to get rid of whatever
you feel.
Get rid of the pleasurable feeling by
wanting to replace it with more of that
pleasure. Get rid of the unpleasurable feeling by
Get rid of the unpleasurable feeling by
wanting to replace it but less
unpleasurable. And getting rid of the neutral feeling
And getting rid of the neutral feeling
by replacing it getting rid of the
discomfort of the neutral feeling by
replacing it with comfortable feeling,
whatever it is.
So, that's what I mean.
You have a choice to not choose to act
out of pressure.
Pressure's there. Fine.
As I said, there is no first point where
you're not pressured and you become
pressured. You wake up and you find
yourself pressured.
That's your point of view. That's your
world. That's your universe.
But you can But you have a choice to
stop acting out of that pressure.
So again, what you said, there is a
diversity of action. Diversity of
choices. Acting and choosing. That's what I mean.
Acting and choosing. That's what I mean.
Like sensuality presents to you, you you
have a choice to say no. Yeah.
You have a choice to be non-reactive to
the pressures. So, that's it still an
action. It's just that you're much more
pressured by other choices and you
choose to choose out of the pressure.
And that's why you keep maintaining the
pressure.
Complete like gratuitous reason that you
choose it.
You choose it cuz you don't understand
it. If you were to understand it, you
would realize it's impossible actually
to choose it.
And it's not a good idea to be choosing
it. Well,
that might that understanding might come
before. Like if you understand it's impossible
Like if you understand it's impossible
to choose it, then it ceases to even be
a possibility as an idea. No, it's
impossible.
Pressure was always secondary to the
experiences at all.
That That was not changed even when I
thought pressure was first in my
experience, my choices, my feelings are
second. No, it was That was just my perception
No, it was That was just my perception
of it. The only perception that I had.
Now you have done it, that's why it's
irreversible. Process of right and wrong
or getting the right view, you can't
reverse it back. You can't forget it.
Cuz it pertains to the nature of your
experience that now you understood. Mhm.
Means you can't ignore it anymore. It's
impossible. The only reason you were
ignoring it is cuz you were not
understanding it.
twist it out of shape. Impossible.
Intentionally. What for what reason? It
cannot be twisted out of shape.
Yeah. Right. Intentionally or unintentionally.
Right. Intentionally or unintentionally.
Um
What is the cessation of action?
Cessation of contact. Cessation of
pressure. Yeah. What is the cessation of
pressure? Well, not acting out of
pressure. That's the vicious circle I
was talking about. See, out of pressure
you act, because of that action you're
pressured. Out of pressure you act, the
fuels the pressure, the fuels the
action, the fuels the pressure, the
fuels the action.
So you got to stop somewhere. It's a
vicious circle. You want
So, start choosing not acting out of
pressure, hence sensory strain. Yeah.
The amazing of that Yeah.
And it And it ties in well with what we
said before. So, it's not like I must
say no to everything. No.
You You need to say no to acting when
you're pressured.
When you feel emotional need to act,
that's when you say no to yourself.
I don't feel emotional need to eat, I'm
simply hungry.
So, I'll eat
for hunger. Yeah.
See, you're learning how to act
not rooted in pressure.
Action is
By refining your action, by making it
less rooted in pressure,
the closer actions out of pressure will
fall off.
By refining your action further, making
it even less less and less rooted in
pressure, what was closer to that will
fall off.
But as I said, it's not a blanket method
that you can just say no to everything
cuz not everything equally pressures
you. Yeah, exactly. You're not understanding
Yeah, exactly. You're not understanding
it. So, that's why we always talk about
you need to know where your motivation
is rooted cuz you're motivated by the
pressure. So, by finding out why you're doing
So, by finding out why you're doing
something you want to do or defending
something you want to defend or want to
gain something you want to gain,
you will find out whether you're
pressured by it or not.
And if you're pressured, you say no to
acting out of pressure.
Yeah, you want to find out what
That's why certain things must be
abandoned cuz they cannot not be rooted
in pressure. Sexual intercourse,
killing, stealing, cheating, lying,
always action in itself cannot be done
in any other way except rooted in
pressure. So, it's not like, "Oh, you can have
So, it's not like, "Oh, you can have
sexual intercourse not being pressured
by sensuality."
And what I said is action. It's
impossible to engage in sensuality
without having perceptions of
sensuality. And perceptions of sensuality are
And perceptions of sensuality are
determined by what? By the pressure of
sensuality. As perceptions are
determined by
So, so yeah, one one begins trying to
understand to understand make things
clear. Try to understand what's
Try to understand what's
You begin that by looking where your
motivation for action and choices is.
Whatever that action and choices are.
Now now I'm now I'm doing it doing it
doing it. I'm getting better at it. Mhm.
I don't you don't you don't even have to
uh
question it that much
if you think it No, cuz you know where
you look. You know where to look.
You know where to look.
Oh yeah. Oh yeah. I'm so familiar with
this thing that when it comes up when
the pressure's there
you know where to look already. Yeah. I
don't have to
go and look at the I look at suit.
Inevitably when people start questioning
things it's going to be at the level of
psychologizing. So well why is this? Why
is that? It's going to be like a you
know Yeah.
an arm's length away. Mhm.
But if you don't
if you don't
don't take that as face value start
questioning your questioning so to
speak. Oh so why do I want to do this?
Well, it's because yesterday such and
such person said this so today I feel
Okay, so can I be more immediate more
accurate? Can I find a more here and now
reason for why I want to do this here
and now?
Not like oh it's because of something
yesterday. That's you choosing that to
be the reason for acting.
Which means even that choice now is
rooted by something more immediate
you're not seeing. So why did you choose
that event that happened yesterday to be
the reason for your action tomorrow?
Uh because that event that happened
yesterday displease me. Make me feel
uncomfortable. So I want to address it tomorrow.
So I want to address it tomorrow.
Mhm. Why? So then it's the discomfort
that's the problem. Not what happened
yesterday. If that which happened yesterday if that
If that which happened yesterday if that
were not uncomfortable would you be
planning dealing with it tomorrow? Uh
no. So what's the more immediate reason
So what's the more immediate reason
for you wanting to deal with it
tomorrow? Uh
I want to deal manage prevent further
discomfort. You're being liable to.
You're being liable to.
Exactly. No, well that's the thing. Why
do you want to prevent the discomfort?
Because I'm liable to it.
So can you prevent your liability to it
by addressing the individual discomfort
that already happened?
No. You remain equally liable.
You remain equally liable.
Some other discomfort is going to arise.
And ask yourself, how many times in the
past you tried to manage discomfort by
addressing this issue, that issue, or
controlling, or psychologizing about it,
figuring it out?
Has that diminished your liability? No,
that just increased your skill of
managing it.
But you're still equally affected by it.
So, what if you were to learn how to not be
what if you were to learn how to not be
affected by it in the first place? Would
there be anything for you to manage?
No. So, why can't I learn
So, why can't I learn
to accept discomfort?
Why do I need to
deal with it, get rid of it, act out of
it? Why do I need, why am I pressured to
choose action that wants to get rid of
discomfort? Well,
Well,
because I never made the opposite effort
of not acting out of discomfort.
Mhm. So, the cessation of
So, the cessation of
contact.
Yeah. Is cessation of kind of that habit
of Cessation of pressure
is basically achieved through not acting
out of pressure that maintains the
pressure. Yeah, which you've been doing. That will
Yeah, which you've been doing. That will
then bring the understanding of it.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
That's what I mean, like
the Dharma
can only be found within Sila, within
sense restraint, within non-sensuality.
Not like after
or or later on a second step. It's
within it. Mhm. So, by being sense
restrained and celebrate and so on, you
are emulating the Dharma.
By emulating it,
you actually have a chance of
understanding what you're creating.
Yeah. Of course, emulating in itself, if
you don't make the effort to understand
it, will not result in understanding.
But it's still wholesome. Mhm. It's
still wholesome to not give in to the
worst type of the the the
of your desire. Or or the one
is that I do it for a week
sensory strength and then I I go back to
sex. Yeah, which means you never
addressed the ultimate value of sexual
intercourse or sensuality. You only try
to ignore it for a week by being sensory
strength. Mhm.
Mhm.
But it's not It needs to be the other
way around. You need to value sensory
strength, celibacy, and non-sexual
activity forever
and then when you do engage with it, it
will be obvious it's because of
weakness. Mhm. And that's how you will
be able to approach it. But if you never
undermine the value of sexual
intercourse or sensuality and only
occasionally abstain yourself from it,
means oh, that's the wrong way around.
You need to undermine the value even if
you don't occasionally abstain from it.
Why? Because by undermining value, you
will occasionally and then much uh
more profoundly and maybe even for the
rest of your life abstain from it.
Cuz you now undermine the view that
sensuality is value. That's what the
Buddha would teach people not like
he would teach them direct sensuality is
dangerous. So the value that you have in
regard to sensual pleasure is wrong
because you value that which is deadly.
You value that which is harmful. You
value that which is factually painful.
And then people say, "Thank you very
much." Get the right view and go back to
that sensuality.
Acts of those sensuality like salt upon
us for example.
But they will never be able to
get rid of now
the view that sensuality is bad. Mhm.
They will be too weak initially if they
choose to not make the effort if they're
satisfied with understanding that
sensuality is really painful.
But they will be too weak to maintain
that standard until they're fully freed
from any sensual itch.
So they might still scratch their itch,
but they will know what they're doing.
They cannot say, "Oh no, sensuality is
not a problem." That's That that the
pernicious view as the Buddha said in
other suttas is when they say there is
no danger in sensuality. Not like
Oh, it's he's restrained or he's not
practicing sense restraint.
That's secondary
to whether you think sensuality is
dangerous or not really that dangerous.
So, that actually that one it was a monk
who was obviously celibate,
sense restrained, but still had the view
that sensuality is not dangerous.
And the Buddha called him amidst the
assembly and absolutely hammered him.
Like called him names and stuff for
holding that ridiculous view because of
which charnel grounds gets filled and so
on. So, it would have been less wrong for
So, it would have been less wrong for
him
to lose his sense restraint
but not adopt the view that sensuality
is not dangerous.
Because if you have a view that
sensuality is dangerous, there is only
so far you can lose your sense
restraint. Literally, you know going
down into this pit will kill me in the
most horrifying death.
So, you can maybe carelessly walk into
it three steps and then you'll be out
cuz the danger will be way it will be
apparent, not like fundamentally
apparent so you'd never even stop your
foot in the cave, step your foot in the
cave. But it's certainly apparent enough for
But it's certainly apparent enough for
you to like do things of of the
diversified nature that would take you
in the hell rooted in those type of
things.
So, that's what I mean. It's that view
that you want to undermine.
But you will never undermine that view
if you don't practice sense restraint at
all even to begin with.
even to begin with.
So, that's why uh generosity, virtue
the mind already the Buddha would say.
So, then he would teach them the danger
of sensuality. Then now they would be
drawn from
to listen to his talk.
And now the danger of and then he would
teach them dhamma and they would get the
right view.
So even if they go back to sensuality to
the whole like lay life, they will never
ever think of sensuality as non-dangerous or
think of sensuality as non-dangerous or
it's fine or it's not a big deal.
Even if they know for the rest of their
life, they will be acting out of weakness.
they will be acting out of weakness.
They're living with family, still
engaging in in in like they're still
always giving the five precepts,
sometimes eight precepts and so on. But
from that point they know they're not
making effort to uproot the danger.
They cannot have the view that it's not
dangerous. So would would I mean it's a ridiculous
So would would I mean it's a ridiculous
thing but uh
that is that such a person would
promote sensuality.
No. So I see the danger. They I'll
promote it for others.
Impossible. Impossible.
I'll promote it. You know
I'm engaging with sensuality cuz I'm
still weak. I will defend the the
danger. And I'm not making effort to uproot my
And I'm not making effort to uproot my
weakness because
well, I family, children, wives and so
on, whatever else back in the day.
So I just have to accept responsibility
for my weakness and be satisfied with
the right view the lord that taught me
that the dangerous sensuality, freedom
from suffering and so on.
But not under any circumstance will I
say, "Oh, it's fine to say that
sensuality is not bad."
Cuz that's far worse than my individual
weakness of engaging with sensuality.
Or saying, "Oh, you shouldn't say that
sensuality is dangerous cuz it might
upset people."
No. You will never ever compromise on the
You will never ever compromise on the
view if you have the right view because
you realize well if you compromise it,
it's not right anymore.
So there's no like, "Oh well, this works
or this doesn't." No.
The views are the right where you know
it what dangerous is dangerous and
non-dangerous is non-dangerous.
One with the right view doesn't cannot
conceal. Exactly. Exactly.
Exactly. Exactly.
For what reason would he? And the truth
is, "Oh, I'm weak. I'm not free from
sensuality." The truth is not, "Oh,
sensuality is not that bad."
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. And that's what I
mean. Person who uttered that, that the
Buddha destroyed in the assembly
was among himself who was restrained
living by the party mocha.
So on the surface he was more restrained
than than your average person. Far more
restrained. That's not why the Buddha criticized him
That's not why the Buddha criticized him
or not criticized or praised him. It was
because he held the view that there is
no danger in sensuality.
I'm restrained and I will be restrained
for the rest of my life but I don't see
this danger in sensuality that the Lord
talks about. There is no obstruction in
obstructive sensuality. It's not
obstruction. Exactly. There's no danger
in it. It's fine. You can do it or not
do it. Up to you. However you feel like
it. I choose to do it to be restrained
but either way there is no obstruction
in it. It's like no that's that's the
core of the problem. Is it even a rule
isn't it? Is it even a rule?
As a novice, yeah.
If you actually there's a monk who was
kicked out of the community. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. If you hold these views that there
is no danger in sensuality.
So you realize okay so that and that
would also you could be be people
something struggle and say so how would
someone like me go back to sensuality?
That's how. He knows he's done out of
weakness. He knows he's responsible for
not making effort to approve that
weakness but what he cannot do is regard
sensuality as not dangerous or as
non-obstructive. So whenever he were to
pick up his practice again
he will do so by abandoning sensuality.
That's why Nekkhamma Sankappa pretty
much thoughts of renunciation, picking
up sense restraint is all that's
necessary for a person with the right
view to develop that right view to
arahantship. If if he's asked is sensuality
If if he's asked is sensuality
good? He would say not a chance. And
then he would say well why are you still
then living with your family? Because
I'm weak.
Ah. There it is. End of the argument. Yeah.
There it is. End of the argument. Yeah.
Okay.
There's authentic authenticity.
But I'm not as weak as a person who is
weak and chooses to mask that weakness
as strength by saying there is no danger
in sensuality.
That's far worse.
And to
get to the last point if we can.
Suffering should be understood. Mhm.
Yeah, I was going to say in the
beginning that's what this whole
principle is. Principle of the four
noble truths. Yeah.
The source and origin should be
understood. What is suffering? Pressure
is suffering. The diversity.
The diversity.
Yeah. There's extreme suffering.
Exactly. suffering. There is beneficial
suffering. There is beneficial
suffering. Suffering that fades slowly,
suffering that fades quickly. Suffering
of the sensory strength is beneficial
suffering. Suffering on account of not
getting enough of what you want is not
beneficial suffering.
Right. Suffering on account of saying no
to your desire is a beneficial
suffering. Cuz it creates a possibility for you to
Cuz it creates a possibility for you to
now understand the nature of acting out
of non-desire.
Or acting out of saying no to desire.
And that that possibility will not exist
for those who don't have even basic
sense sense sensory strength. Mhm.
What is the cessation?
Suffering. The cessation of craving.
Mhm. Which is it? Which is that very thing
Which is it? Which is that very thing
that feels the contact, the pressure.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
And
uh
Could you say that the sotapanna
who has understood some It's clear It's
very so clear. That's why he's a
sotapanna. First of all, he understands
what suffering is, what leads to
suffering, what diminish.
What he's free from it.
In a way that's that's very much
what frees you.
Yeah. See like like imagine you're trapped in
See like like imagine you're trapped in
the house
and the the roof is basically eroding,
falling down on you bit by bit and you
don't know how to escape.
The real suffering there is that fear
of not being able to escape, what will
happen. That's the the that's the despair.
That's the the that's the despair.
The terror.
But then imagine you figure out a way
out and then you look at the roof and say,
and then you look at the roof and say,
"I still have time."
Cuz you do, in a way.
But of course, from our heart's point of
view, even that's careless. That's why
they would would urge and cause
evoke sense of urgency in sotapannas,
sakadagamis, and anagamis because they
as he said, they still have work to do.
But knowing the way out of that
crumbling house
will free you from that fundamental
existential fear
of not knowing the way out.
step out here.
I can just step out.
There's my door and I'm right here.
And that's why many sotapannas would
like become sotapannas or even like many
others become arahants at the moment of
death cuz the moment of death is the
moment of being thrown out.
Yeah, cuz you know the way out.
Cuz you know the way out and that's what
you understood.
But for for the for the person with the
right view Mhm. he knows which
which direction is Nibbana, which which
way leads to Nibbana.
Yeah, he knows where Nibbana is.
Yes. Yeah. He now just needs to um
adhere to it He doesn't have to start
again He doesn't have to now start again each
He doesn't have to now start again each
time. Is Is sensuality bad? No, of
course, cuz he's beyond he's free
himself from doubt.
It's so clear.
He cannot doubt it. It's so clear he
cannot doubt it. It's so
that is so clear that he can he cannot
doubt it, but he
he he knows what to do then then and
there. And he knows what to do because
he cannot doubt it.
That's why he doesn't need to
Oh, so is this bad? He understood it's
bad and even the question is this bad
it's meaningless cuz the understanding
that it's bad it's clear. Yeah, it's
Become completely familiar.
And not like familiar with all this
information. No, simply familiar with where the
No, simply familiar with where the
problem is.
Knowing problem as a problem and
non-problem as non-problem.
Is it what's it a quick wisdom that kind
of
uh
lightning wisdom? What was it? It's with
yes, seeing things as they are, yeah.
But that takes time to develop.
But that takes time.
have the quick wisdom necessarily that
quick. But if it's quick sufficiently
enough Yeah, so to speak. But it is not
quick wisdom in the sense that it's
quickly responds to the reason problem.
Wisdom basically means when you see
beyond the reason problem you cannot not
see the nature of the problem.
Yeah, yeah. That's That's It's so clear.
noble truth is the truth of suffering.
That's where the problem is.
So you cannot mistake
non-problem as problem.
By knowing what the problem is, you then
know how that problem is there.
Why that Why that is a problem.
By knowing why that is a problem, you
know then what it isn't a problem. Thus
you will know the way out of the
problem. So the four noble truths are basically
So the four noble truths are basically
one insight
in these different directions.
Understanding suffering means
understanding the way out of it.
Because suffering is not about figuring
out information.
It's not about things that make you
suffer. Suffering is about not resisting
Suffering is about not resisting
pain
not leaning towards pleasure, not
leaning away from pain
and not kind of turning a blind eye to
neither pleasure nor pain.
That is the root of suffering and that's
what he has understood.
Thus no matter of things that come from
the world can be mistaken as suffering.
Only craving arises, only craving
ceases. Or as those in
Theragatha the verses when when like Mara comes and
the verses when when like Mara comes and
tries to
sort of
disturb their mind. Oh, is this or what
if they What if the robbers come and say
like, what are we doing about? What
There's nothing for me to protect.
None of the things that being threatened
even by possible robber or rapist or
whatever else,
none of those things are suffering.
Craving is the suffering, basically.
Suffering within this arises, suffering
ceases on its own because craving
arises, craving ceases on its own.
All I have to do is not act out of it
cuz now I understood it.
So, there is no other problem.
Who are you talking about when you say,
"Oh, you should do this or defend that
or run away from this forest?" Who are
you talking about?
See, the only reason you would run out
of the way of forest is cuz it makes you
suffer. Which means you don't see that
suffering that you feel is the problem,
you think the forest is the problem.
No, so it's only suffering arises,
suffering ceases. What else is there?
Nothing. That's what the Buddha said, "All All I
That's what the Buddha said, "All All I
teach,
I mean, as many suttas as there are,
all I teach is suffering and freedom
from it. Everything else he ever said is
within that."
Suffering from it. So, this all simplifies to the
from it. So, this all simplifies to the
clarity is So, to me, the clarity of
sotapanna is not the clarity The clarity
of sotapanna is, "Ah,
This is one man. There is suffering,
there is freedom from suffering. That's
what matters. That's the only thing that
matters. Resisting a feeling or not
doing so.
That's all the only thing that matters.
Cuz by not resisting a feeling, you
cease to cultivate the craving.
Craving is that leaning towards
pleasure. Leaning is not in the pleasure. Leaning
Leaning is not in the pleasure. Leaning
is your that subtle attitude or leaning
away from pain. Or hiding. Or just
turning a blind eye to neutral feeling
cuz it's just too
ambiguous. You need something more defined.
You need something more defined.
Pressure, craving, contact.
Same thing. Craving and contact. Well,
exactly. Yeah, yeah. Pressure. Yeah.
It's It's
Pressure, feeling, contact, yeah.
Pressure, feeling, craving, sorry. Yeah.